<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./OpenSocial.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
"http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="full3978"
     docName="opensocial-core-api-server-specification-2-5-0"
     xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">
 <front>
  <title abbrev="Core-API-Server">OpenSocial Core API Server Specification 2.5.0</title>
  <author fullname="OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group">
   <address>
    <email>opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
<date month="March" year="2012" />
  <abstract>
   <t>This document describes a method for making information
   and services programatically available on the internet.</t>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <middle>
  <section title="Notation and Conventions">
   <section title="Requirements">
    <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in 
    <xref target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>
    <t>An implementation is not compliant if it fails to satisfy one or more of
    the MUST or REQUIRED level requirements for the protocols it
    implements.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Conventions">
    <t>Domain name examples use 
    <xref target="RFC2606"/>.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Augmented BNF">
    <t>The grammatical rules in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in <xref target="RFC2234"/>.  The following constructs are introduced in this document to augment 
    RFC2234:</t>
    <list style="hanging">
     <t hangText="{rule1 rule2}">
      <t>Elements enclosed in braces (squiggly brackets) are treated as a
      single, UNORDERED element. Its contents may occur in any order. Hence: 
      <artwork type="abnf" xml:space="preserve">{elem foo} bar</artwork>
      would match (elem foo bar) and (foo elem bar).</t>
      <t>NOTE: Specifying alternatives is quite different from specifying set
      grouping. Alternatives indicate the matching of exactly one (sub-)rule
      out of the total grouping. The set mechanism indicates the matching of a
      string which contains all of the elements within the group; however the
      elements may occur in any order.</t>
     </t>
     <t hangText="#rule">A construct "#" is defined, similar to "*", for
     defining lists of elements. The full form is "&lt;n&gt;#&lt;m&gt;element"
     indicating at least &lt;n&gt; and at most &lt;m&gt; elements, each
     separated by one or more commas (",") and OPTIONAL linear white space
     (LWS). This makes the usual form of lists very easy; a rule such as 
     <artwork type="inline" xml:space="preserve">( *LWS element *( *LWS "," *LWS element ))</artwork>
     can be shown as 
     <artwork type="inline" xml:space="preserve">1#element</artwork>
     Wherever this construct is used, null elements are allowed, but do
     not contribute to the count of elements present. That is, "(element), ,
     (element) " is permitted, but counts as only two elements. Therefore, 
     where at least one element is required, at least one non-null element MUST 
     be present.  Default values are 0 and infinity so that "#element" allows 
     any number, including zero; "1#element" requires at least one; and 
     "1#2element" allows one or two.</t>
     <t hangText="&amp;rule">A construct "&amp;" is defined, similar to "#",
     which uses an ampersand (&amp;) instead of commas, and MUST NOT include
     linear white space between elements.</t>
     <t hangText="implied *LWS">The grammar described by this specification is
     word-based. Except where noted otherwise, linear white space (LWS) can be
     included between any two adjacent words (token or quoted-string), and
     between adjacent words and separators, without changing the interpretation
     of a field. At least one delimiter (LWS and/or separators) MUST exist
     between any two tokens, since they would otherwise be interpreted as a
     single token.</t>
    </list>
   </section>
   <section title="Basic Rules">
    <t>The following rules are used throughout this specification to describe
    basic parsing constructs. The US-ASCII coded character set is defined by 
    <xref target="RFC20" /> </t>
    <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<![CDATA[
OCTET          = <any 8-bit sequence of data>
CHAR           = <any US-ASCII character (octets 0 - 127)>
UPALPHA        = <any US-ASCII uppercase letter "A".."Z">
LOALPHA        = <any US-ASCII lowercase letter "a".."z">
ALPHA          = UPALPHA / LOALPHA
DIGIT          = <any US-ASCII digit "0".."9">
CTL            = <any US-ASCII control character (octets 0 - 31) and DEL (127)>
CR             = <US-ASCII CR, carriage return (13)>
LF             = <US-ASCII LF, linefeed (10)>
SP             = <US-ASCII SP, space (32)>
HT             = <US-ASCII HT, horizontal-tab (9)>
<">            = <US-ASCII double-quote mark (34)>
CRLF           = CR LF
LWS            = [CRLF] 1*( SP / HT )
TEXT           = <any OCTET except CTLs, but including LWS>
COMMA          = <US-ASCII comma (44)>
      ]]>
</artwork>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Protocols">
   <t>OpenSocial defines REST and RPC protocols to allow remote clients access to server side data. The data formats are independent of the protocols used in requests and common data types and formats are described in the <xref target="Core-Data">Core Data Specification</xref>. Common data types for social applications are documented in the <xref target="Social-Data">Social Data Specification</xref>.</t>
   <section title="REST">
   <t>The REST protocol defines a language and platform neutral protocol for clients to
   interact with OpenSocial container servers outside of gadgets on a web page.
   As a protocol, it is intended to be reasonably easy to implement in any
   language and on any platform. It should also be usable across a range of
   clients, from gadgets operating within a web page to servers communicating
   to synchronize data about a user.</t>
   <t>API Servers MUST support the REST protocol.</t>
   <t>The protocol operates primarily in terms of resources and operations on
   them. It is defined on top of the HTTP protocol, and uses the standard HTTP
   methods (GET, POST, PUT, DELETE, etc.) to retrieve and change server
   state.</t>
   <t>No single data representation is ideal for every client. This protocol
   defines representations for each resource in three widely supported formats,
   <xref target="RFC4627">JSON</xref>, XML, and 
   <xref target="RFC4287">Atom</xref> /
   <xref target="RFC5023">AtomPub</xref>, using a set of generic mapping rules.
   The mapping rules allow a server to write to a single interface rather than
   implementing the protocol three times.</t>
   <x:deprecated note="ATOM Support" href="http://code.google.com/p/opensocial-resources/issues/detail?id=1152">
   <t>Support for the ATOM format is being deprecated in the OpenSocial 2.0 release.  Consumers should start migrating to using <xref target="RFC4627">JSON</xref> or XML representations.</t>
   </x:deprecated>
   <t>OpenSocial container servers are free to define additional
   representations but MUST support at least the JSON and Atom formats for all
   resources and XML for the people calls. XML MAY be supported for the rest of
   the resources.</t>
   <t>Most operations consist of retrieving (GET), updating (PUT), creating (POST or
   PUT), or destroying (DELETE) these resources. It also specifies an optional
   partial update feature which avoids sending large resources over the wire to
   update just one field.</t>
    <section title="REST Request" anchor="REST-Request">
     <t>A REST request uses the following format:</t>
     <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>REST-Request</x:highlight>     = <x:ref>REST-HTTP-Method</x:ref> SP <x:ref>REST-Request-URI</x:ref> SP &lt;any valid HTTP version identifier&gt; CRLF
                   { 
                     "HOST: " &lt;any valid HTTP host&gt; CRLF
                     [ "Authorization: " <x:ref>Auth-Token</x:ref> CRLF ]
                     [ "Content-Type: " <x:ref>Content-Type</x:ref> CRLF ]
                     [ *(&lt;a valid HTTP header not defined above&gt; CRLF) ]
                   }
                   CRLF
                   [ <x:ref>REST-Request-Payload</x:ref> ]
</artwork>
     <t>For example, here is a REST request to retrieve information about a
     user:</t>
     <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
GET /api/people/@me/@self?fields=name HTTP/1.1
Host: api.example.org
Authorization: hh5s93j4hdidpola
Content-Type: application/json
</artwork>
     <section title="REST-HTTP-Method"
             anchor="REST-HTTP-Method">
      <t>Each REST resource defined in this document may specify the exact
     semantics of each method, but generally, "GET" is associated with
     retrieving a resource, "POST" is associated with creating a resource,
     "PUT" is associated with updating a resource, and "DELETE" is associated
     with deleting a resource.</t>
      <t>The following HTTP methods may be used for REST requests:</t>
      <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>REST-HTTP-Method</x:highlight> = "GET" / "POST" / "PUT" / "DELETE" 
</artwork>
   <t>POST is special; it
   operates on collections and creates new activities, persons, or app data
   within those collections, and returns the base URI for the created resource
   in the Location: header, per AtomPub semantics.</t>
   <t>Restricted clients, or
   clients behind restricted clients, which cannot use PUT or DELETE SHOULD
   translate PUT and DELETE to POST operations with an additional
   X-HTTP-Method-Override: header: </t>
   <figure>
    <artwork xml:space="preserve">
POST /... HTTP/1.1
...
X-HTTP-Method-Override: PUT
</artwork>
   </figure>
   <t>Servers SHOULD respond to POST+X-HTTP-Method-Override as if the
   content of the header were the actual operation sent.</t>
   <t>Note that OpenSocial
   does not support cross-domain JSONP (GET with callback), but servers MAY
   offer this as an extension. It is RECOMMENDED that such servers implement
   appropriate security and authorization controls.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="REST-Request-URI" anchor="REST-Request-URI">
      <t>The request URI is composed from the base path, a URI fragment, and optional query parameters.</t> 
      <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>REST-Request-URI</x:highlight> = <x:ref>REST-Base-Path</x:ref> <x:ref>REST-URI-Fragment</x:ref> ["?" <x:ref>REST-Query-Parameters</x:ref>]
</artwork>
      <section title="REST-Base-Path"
             anchor="REST-Base-Path">
       <t>An OpenSocial REST server may choose to expose their REST endpoints in
     a "namespaced" way through use of a path. For example, the REST resource
     of "http://www.example.com/apis/people" would have a REST base path of
     "/apis", while "http://www.example.com/apis/opensocial-1.0/people" would
     correspond with the REST base path of "/apis/opensocial-1.0".</t>
       <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>REST-Base-Path</x:highlight> = String
</artwork>
      </section>
      <section title="REST-URI-Fragment"
             anchor="REST-URI-Fragment">
       <t>The URI fragment defines the exact resource that a request is targeting.  Each service defines the format and possible values for the URI fragment based on the resources the service exposes.</t>
       <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>REST-URI-Fragment</x:highlight> = String
</artwork>
   <t>Each service type defines an associated partial URI format. The base URI
   for each service is found in the URI element associated with the service in
   the discovery document. Each service type accepts parameters via the URL
   path. Definitions are of the form:</t>
   <figure>
    <artwork xml:space="preserve">
{a}/{b}/{c}
</artwork>
   </figure>
   <t>Parameters must be filled in using left to right ordering. If a
   positional pattern is missing, no parameters to the right of that parameter
   may be filled in. For example, if the preceding pattern was used and only
   the value of the a parameter was known and set to @me, the complete URL
   would be expressed as: </t>
   <figure>
    <artwork xml:space="preserve">
[Discovery URI]/@me
</artwork>
   </figure>
      </section>
      <section title="REST-Query-Parameters" anchor="REST-Query-Parameters">
       <x:anchor-alias value="REST-Query-Parameters" />
       <x:anchor-alias value="ENCODE-REST-PARAMETER" />
       <t>Additional parameters for a REST request MAY be passed via the
     querystring portion of the request URI.</t>
       <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>REST-Query-Parameters</x:highlight> = &amp;ENCODE-REST-PARAMETER(k,v)
</artwork>
       <t>This specification defines a function ENCODE-REST-PARAMETER, which
     is an alias for encoding a key/value pair.  The PCT-ENCODE function 
     is described in section 2.1 of <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>
       <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
ENCODE-REST-PARAMETER(k,v) = PCT-ENCODE(k) "=" PCT-ENCODE(FLATTEN(v))
</artwork>  
       <t>The FLATTEN function is also defined in this spec, and behaves in
     the following manner:</t>
       <list style="numbers">
        <t>If the argument supplied is an array of strings or numbers, the 
      string representation of each array element is returned, with each element
      separated by a COMMA.</t>
        <t>If the argument supplied is a string or a number, the string 
      representation of the argument is returned.</t>
       </list>
       <t>The behavior of FLATTEN for input not explicitly covered here is 
     undefined.  This includes associative arrays, or nested arrays.</t>
       <t>Here is an example of a REST request URL with query parameters.  Note that the fields parameter demonstrates a flattened array:</t>
       <artwork type="abnf">        
http://www.example.com/opensocial/rest/people/@me/@self?fields=name,gender&amp;format=json
</artwork>
      </section>
     </section>
     <section title="REST-Request-Payload"
              anchor="REST-Request-Payload">
      <t>A REST request MAY carry a payload, such as an object to create on the server.  Each service defines which requests support a payload and the format of the payload.</t>
     </section>
    </section>
    <section title="REST Response" anchor="REST-Response">
     <t>A REST response uses the following format:</t>
     <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
HTTP/1.x <x:ref>HTTP-Status-Code</x:ref> 
[ "Content-Type: " <x:ref>Content-Type</x:ref> ]
[ REST-Response-Payload ]
</artwork>
     <section title="REST-Response-Payload" anchor="REST-Response-Payload">
       <t>A REST request MAY contain a payload.  Each service method defines the object that is included as the Return-Object. The payload uses the following format:</t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
REST-Response-Payload = "&lt;response xmlns='http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial'&gt;"
                          <x:ref>Return-Object</x:ref>
                        "&lt;/response&gt;"
</artwork>
     </section>
    </section>
   </section>
   
   <section title="RPC">
    <t>The RPC protocol supports
   the same data and operations as the RESTful API in a form that is more
   natural for the JSON data format. Any batch of RPCs should be
   programatically convertible to a sequence or batch of RESTful calls and
   maintain the same semantics, any exception to this will be called out
   explicitly.</t>
    <t>API Servers MAY support the RPC protocol.</t>
    <t>The RPC protocol shares the following with the RESTful protocol:</t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>The JSON/XML format of the OpenSocial data types such as Person, Activity,
    Group, AppData are identical.</t>
     <t>HTTP status codes are used to represent common error cases where
    applicable.</t>
     <t><xref target="OAuth-Core-1.0" /> is supported for authentication and
    authorization in addition to other authorization schemes a container may
    choose to support. A single OAuth token can be used for a batch of
    operations or each operation can specify its own OAuth token.</t>
     <t>Concurrency control is optional.</t>
    </list>
    <t>The RPC protocol differs from the RESTful protocol in the following ways:</t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Conforms to the <xref target="JSON-RPC" /> specification</t>
     <t>All structural elements in the protocol are represented using the JSON
    or XML notation.</t>
     <t>Batch support is required.</t>
     <t>HTTP is used primarily as a transport and not to indicate the semantics
    of the request.</t>
     <t>Automated discovery happens in two steps. XRDS can be used to discover
    the RPC endpoint. The service can then be introspected by executing a request to the <xref target="System-Service-ListMethods">system.listMethods</xref> method to discover the list of available services and
    operations using conventions defined by <xref target="XML-RPC-Introspection">XML-RPC Introspection</xref>. In general it is expected
    that a large percentage of consumers will bypass automated discovery and
    rely on simply hardcoding references to the endpoints of various popular
    containers.</t>
    </list>
  <section title="URL Addressing"
           anchor="urlAddressing">
   <t>Containers MUST give access to the RPC services using a URL addressing
   scheme to invoke a single RPC via HTTP GET. This encoding can also be used
   to support RPC execution via form posts including file-uploads as parameters
   to RPCs. It is recommended that only services that are idempotent are
   exported in this manner. Containers MUST use the following canonical
   transformation between the RPC structure and its URL encoding:</t>
   <list style="symbols">
    <t>The RPC method is defined by the 'method' query parameter</t>
    <t>The RPC id is defined by the 'id' query parameter</t>
    <t>All other query parameters are assumed to belong to the RPC params
    element and are encoded from JSON using &lt;field path dot
    notation&gt;=&lt;scalar value&gt; | &lt;comma separated array of
    scalars&gt;. When a field represents an array of non-scalars then elements
    of the array are identified by enclosing the index in parenthesis. Strings
    which match [0-9]+ MUST be single-quoted, Strings which match [A-Za-z_]+
    MUST be unquoted, all other strings retain their original quoting.</t>
   </list>
   <t>The following provides some examples of mapping JSON objects to URL Parameters:</t>
    <texttable align="left">
     <ttcol align="left">JSON Object</ttcol>
     <ttcol align="left">URL Parameter</ttcol>
     <c>{ "field" : "value" }</c><c>field=value</c>
     <c>{ "field" : [1,2,3,4,5]}</c><c>field=1,2,3,4,5</c>
     <c>{ "field" : "12" }</c><c>field='12'</c>
     <c>{ "field" :
[identifier,anotheridentifier]}</c><c>field=identifier,anotheridentifier</c>
     <c>{ "field" : ["value","another value"]}</c><c>field=value,"another
value"</c>
     <c>{ "field" : ['value','another value']}</c><c>field=value,'another
value'</c>
     <c>{ "field" : { "nested" : "value" }}</c><c>field.nested=value</c>
     <c>{ "field" : [{ "nested1" : "value1" }, { "nested2" : "value2"
}]}</c><c>field(0).nested1=value1&amp;field(1).nested2=value2</c>
    </texttable>   
   <t>For example, given the following <x:ref>RPC-Request-Payload</x:ref>:</t>
   <artwork type="example">
{ "method" : "people.get", "id" : "myfriends", "params": {"userId" : "@me", "groupId" : "@friends" } } 
</artwork>
   <t>The corresponding URL is:</t>
   <artwork type="example">
http://api.example.org/rpc?method=people.get&amp;id=myfriends&amp;params.userId=@me&amp;params.groupId=@friends
</artwork>
   <t>In situations where containers support the 
   <xref target="urlAddressing">URL Addressing</xref> scheme to perform an RPC
   the container MAY return arbitrary content types in the response other than
   application/json. The system.methodHelp operation relies on this to provide
   browseable documentation.</t>
  </section>

    <section title="RPC Request"
             anchor="RPC-Request">
     <t>An RPC request uses the following format:</t>
     <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
RPC-Request = "POST /" <x:ref>RPC-Base-URL</x:ref> " HTTP/1.1"
              "HOST" &lt;any valid HTTP host&gt;
              "Authorization: " <x:ref>Auth-Token</x:ref> 
              "Content-Type: " <x:ref>Content-Type</x:ref> 
              <x:ref>RPC-Request-Payload</x:ref>
</artwork>
     <t>For example, here is a RPC request to retrieve information about a
     user:</t>
     <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
POST /rpc HTTP/1.1
Host: api.example.org
Authorization: hh5s93j4hdidpola
Content-Type: application/json
{
  "method" : "people.get",
  "id" : "myself"
  "params" : {
    "userId" : "@me",
    "groupId" : "@self"
  }
}
</artwork>
     <section title="RPC Base URL"
              anchor="RPC-Base-URL">
      <t>The RPC Base URL is defined in the XRDS file.</t>
     </section>
     <section title="RPC Request Payload"
              anchor="RPC-Request-Payload">
      <t>RPC requests MAY batch multiple procedure calls into a single HTTP
      request. Therefore, the payload of an RPC request can container a JSON
      array of procedure calls, or a single procedure call:</t>
      <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>RPC-Request-Payload</x:highlight> = RPC-Batch-Payload / RPC-Single-Payload
<x:highlight>RPC-Batch-Payload</x:highlight> = "[" #RPC-Single-Payload "]"
<x:highlight>RPC-Single-Payload</x:highlight> = "{"
                        &lt;"&gt; "method" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;"&gt; <x:ref>RPC-Method</x:ref> &lt;"&gt; ","
                        &lt;"&gt; "id" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;"&gt; <x:ref>Request-ID</x:ref> &lt;"&gt; ","
                        [ &lt;"&gt; "params" &lt;"&gt; ":" <x:ref>RPC-Request-Parameters</x:ref> ]
                      "}"
</artwork>
      <t>Note that the "json-rpc" property defined in <xref target="JSON-RPC">JSON-RPC</xref> is not passed in the request but requests MUST be interpreted as if "json-rpc" : "2.0" was supplied.</t>
      <t>If a method call has no parameters, or only default values are required, the "params" field can be omitted completely.</t>
      <t>Here is an example of a RPC request with a batch of procedure calls in
      the payload:</t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
POST /rpc HTTP/1.1
Host: api.example.org
Authorization: hh5s93j4hdidpola
Content-Type: application/json
[
  {
    "method" : "people.get",
    "id" : "myself",
    "params" : {
      "userId" : "@me",
      "groupId" : "@self"
    }
  },
  {
    "method" : "people.get",
    "id" : "myfriends",
    "params" : {
      "userId" : "@me",
      "groupId" : "@friends"
    }
  }
]
</artwork>
      <t>Note that multiple authorization tokens MAY be used in a single batch request. The following example contains an authorization token as an HTTP header in the request, which is overridden by an authorization token provided in the 'auth' property in the second request object of the batch.  In this example, assume that Alice doesn't have access to Bob's profile, so her authorization token is not sufficient to access his information.  The client making the request has an authorization token for Bob's profile, so the client can include this token to retrieve his information as well.  For more information on authentication and authorization, see <xref target="Security">Security</xref>.</t>
      <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
POST /rpc HTTP/1.1
Host: api.example.org
Authorization: &lt;1st Auth token&gt;
Content-Type: application/json
[
  {
    "method" : "people.get",
    "id" : "profileOfAlice"
    "params: {
      "userId" : "09737549474",
    }
  },
  {
    "method" : "people.get",
    "id" : "profileOfBob",
    "params: {
      "userId" : "34906734059",
      "auth" : "&lt;2nd Auth token&gt;"
    }
  }
]
</artwork>
     </section>
     <section title="RPC Method"
               anchor="RPC-Method">
    <t>The value of the "method" field in an OpenSocial RPC request uses a
    format of "&lt;service-name&gt;.&lt;operation&gt;". &lt;service-name&gt; is
    a string [A-Za-z0-9_]+ that identifies one of the services listed in
    [Services] and &lt;operation&gt; is a string [A-Za-z0-9_]+ that identifies
    an operation supported by that service.</t>
       <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>RPC-Method</x:highlight>   = &lt;"&gt; Service-Name "." Method-Name &lt;"&gt;
<x:highlight>Service-Name</x:highlight> = String
<x:highlight>Method-Name</x:highlight>  = String
</artwork>
    <t>All OpenSocial services MUST expose a "get" operation. Operations with the names get, create, update and delete should map to the HTTP equivalent operations in the RESTful protocol of
    GET, PUT, POST &amp; DELETE.</t>
       <t>Available methods can be determined by calling the 
       <xref target="System-Service-ListMethods">system.listMethods</xref> method.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="RPC Request Parameters"
               anchor="RPC-Request-Parameters">
       <x:anchor-alias value="ENCODE-RPC-PARAMETER" />
       <t>Parameters can be passed to RPC methods in the request payload as a
       JSON object as described in <xref target="RFC4627"/></t>
       <t>Appropriate values for RPC request parameters can be determined by
       calling the 
       <x:ref target="System-Service-MethodSignatures">system.methodSignatures</x:ref> method.</t>
       <t>Here is an example of an RPC request payload with procedure-specific
       parameters (userId, groupId) and standard OpenSocial parameters:</t>
       <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
{
  "method" : "people.get",
  "id" : "myself"
  "params" : {
    "userId" : "@me",
    "groupId" : "@self",
    "fields" : "name, gender",
    "format" : "json"
  }
}</artwork>
       <t>This specification defines a function ENCODE-RPC-PARAMETER which is
       an alias for the JSON encoding process.  This function takes a key and
       value as arguments, where the key must be a string, and the value must
       have a valid JSON encoding.</t>
       <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">ENCODE-RPC-PARAMETER(k,v) = "{" &lt;"&gt; k &lt;"&gt; ":" JSON-ENCODE(v) "}")</artwork>
     </section>
    </section>
    <section title="RPC Response"
             anchor="RPC-Response">
     <t>An RPC response uses the following format:</t>
     <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
HTTP/1.x 207 Multi-Status
"Content-Type: " <x:ref>Content-Type</x:ref> 
<x:ref>RPC-Response-Payload</x:ref>
</artwork>
     <section title="RPC-Response-Payload"
              anchor="RPC-Response-Payload">
      <t>RPC responses MAY contain results from multiple procedure calls, if
      the corresponding HTTP request contained a 
      <x:ref>RPC-Batch-Payload</x:ref>.  The batch response elements MUST be returned in the same order
     as the corresponding batch request elements and the "id" property of the corresponding
     request in the batch request MUST be carried over to the response. If processing of the entire batch fails, as opposed to a single request within the batch, then the returned value is a single 
      <x:ref>RPC-Error</x:ref> object with the appropriate error message and
      code.</t>
      <t>The response payload for a single procedure call MUST contain an 'id'
      property to correlate the response with a request. On success, the
      payload MUST contain a 'result' property. On failure, the payload MUST contain an 'error'
      property.  Each service method defines the object that is included as the Return-Object.</t>
      <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>RPC-Response-Payload</x:highlight> = RPC-Batch-Payload / RPC-Single-Payload
<x:highlight>RPC-Batch-Payload</x:highlight> = <x:ref>RPC-Error</x:ref> / ("[" #RPC-Single-Payload"]")
<x:highlight>RPC-Single-Payload</x:highlight> = "{"
                       &lt;"&gt; "id" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;"&gt; <x:ref>Request-ID</x:ref> &lt;"&gt; ","
                       ( (&lt;"&gt; "result" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;Return-Object&gt;) / (&lt;"&gt; "error" &lt;"&gt; ":" <x:ref>RPC-Error</x:ref>) )
                     "}"
</artwork>
      <t>The following examples illustrate how success and failure are
      represented in responses to batch requests. 
      <t>Batch successful, all procedure calls successful:</t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
[
  { 
    "id" : "myself", 
    "result" : { ... }
  },
  { 
    "id" : "myfriends", 
    "result" : { ... }
  }           
]
</artwork>
      <t>Batch successful, some procedure calls successful while some fail:</t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
[
  { 
    "id" : "myself", 
    "result" : { ... }
  },
  { 
    "id" : "myfriends", 
    "error" : { ... }
  }
]
</artwork>
      <t>Batch successful, all procedure calls fail:</t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
[
  { 
    "id" : "myself", 
    "error" : { ... }
  },
  { 
    "id" : "myfriends", 
    "error" : { ... }
  }
]
</artwork>
      <t>Batch fails:</t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
{
  "error" : { ... }
}
</artwork></t>
     </section>
     <section title="RPC Error"
              anchor="RPC-Error">
      <t>An error object MUST contain a 'code' property to indicate the actual
      error that occurred and MAY contain a 'message' property describing the
      error. Additional information may be returned in the 'data' property, as
      defined by the procedure.</t>
      <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
RPC-Error = "{"
              [ &lt;"&gt; "message" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;"&gt; string &lt;"&gt; "," ]
              [ &lt;"&gt; "data" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;any JSON object&gt; "," ]
              &lt;"&gt; "code" &lt;"&gt; ":" integer ","
            "}"
</artwork>

      <t>A common set of error codes are used to represent failure modes that
   apply generally to operations and so are reserved for use by this
   specification.</t>
      <texttable align="left">
       <ttcol align="left">Code</ttcol>
       <ttcol align="left">Meaning</ttcol>
       <c>-32700 (Parse error)</c>
       <c>Invalid JSON. An error occurred on the server while parsing the JSON
       text.</c>
       <c>-32600 (Invalid Request)</c>
       <c>The received JSON not a valid JSON-RPC or batch of JSON-RPCs.</c>
       <c>-32601 (Method not found)</c>
       <c>The requested remote-procedure does not exist / is not available.</c>
       <c>-32602 (Invalid params)</c>
       <c>Invalid method parameters.</c>
       <c>-32603 (Internal server error)</c>
       <c>Internal server error.</c>
       <c>-32099..-32000</c>
       <c>Reserved for implementation-defined server-errors.</c>
       <c>401 (Unauthorized)</c>
       <c>Access token does not grant access to the resource,</c>
       <c>404 (Not Found)</c>
       <c>The requested resource was not found.</c>
       <c>409 (Conflict)</c>
       <c>The requested update conflicts with a prior change.</c>
       <c>0-1000</c>
       <c>Reserved for future use by this specification.</c>
      </texttable>
      <t>Here is an example of an unsuccessful RPC response payload:</t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
{
  "id" : "myself"
  "error" : {
    "code" : 401
    "message" : "The authorization token does not provide access to the requested resource."
  }
}
</artwork>
     </section>
    </section>
   </section>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Security" anchor="Security"> 

   <t>OpenSocial Containers MUST support TLS 2.0 / SSL connections for sensitive data 
      since OAuth on its own does not provide encryption or message body integrity checking.
      Note that TLS 2.0/SSL is required with many scenarios in the OAuth 2.0 specification.</t> 
   <section title="OAuth 1.0a Support">
   <t>Core Gadget Servers MUST support Open Authorization 1.0a <xref target="OAuth-Core-1.0" /> 
      but SHOULD use appropriate policies to determine which operations are allowed on a per-consumer and 
      per-user basis.</t>
    <t>When OAuth 1.0a is used for authorization on a single RPC, the OAuth signature
        uses the <xref target="urlAddressing">URL Addressing</xref> representation of the
        request without the authorization parameter, in order to calculate the signature base string.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="OAuth 2.0 Support">
   <xref target="Issue-1138">Discussion</xref>
     <t>Core Gadget Servers MUST support the authorization server, resource server and client roles
      defined in section 1.1 of the Open Authorization 2.0 specification <xref target="draft-ietf-oauth-v2-22"/>.</t>
     <t>A Core Gadget Server MUST provide authorization, token issuance and resource access endpoints per the OAuth 2
      specification.
      A Core Gadget Server MUST implement the authorization code and client credential types described in section 4 of the
      Open Authorization 2.0 specification.  Core Gadget Servers SHOULD implement the implicit grant type.
      Core Gadget Servers MAY implement the refresh token pattern described 
      in section 1.5 of  the OAuth 2.0 specification.</t>
     </section>
    <section title="Two Party OAuth Optional Parameters">
      <t>For 2 party (client credential) OAuth requests, if a Core Gadget Server has a user identifier
      and wishes to indicate that the
      operation is being done on behalf of that particular user, it SHOULD provide
      the OAuth extension parameter xoauth_requestor_id along with the OAuth
      parameters as a query fragment.  Often times, the value for the xoauth_reqeustor_id
      will be set to the e-mail address of the 
      user, on who's behalf the Core Gadget Server is making the call.
      Core Gadget Servers SHOULD only provide the xoauth_requestor_id if the user has given prior
      consent to the operation or class of operations being done on their behalf.
      Core Gadget Servers MUST either honor the parameter or ignore it as if it were not
      provided.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Client Registration">
      <t>OpenSocial Containers may wish to restrict requests from unknown clients and require gadget registration, 
      in order to mitigate risk. OpenSocial Containers SHOULD document how to register a gadget with the OpenSocial
      Container in order to obtain a client identifier and client secret.  This is typically done through a web page,
      although the exact method is left to the specific implementation.</t>
      <t>Note that per the security considerations 
      mentioned in the OAuth 2.0 specification, client secrets should not be issued to untrusted clients.</t>
      <xref target="Issue-1138">Discussion</xref>
      <t>OpenSocial Containers SHOULD document how to store client identifiers and client secrets on the server in order for
      a gadget running locally to access remote data in another server.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Redirection during 3 Party OAuth">
      <t>OpenSocial Containers SHOULD document how the OpenSocial Container handles redirection when authenticating
      a user and obtaining authorization for a gadget. Note that this is a potential vector for phishing if the 
      user is required to enter their credentials.  Normally, for three-party OAuth exchanges, the OpenSocial 
      Container will provide a web page 
      to collect authentication and scoped authorization information, although the exact method is left to the 
      specific implementation.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>OpenSocial Containers SHOULD base their security decisions on the type of client in use; 
      a generally available desktop client, for example, cannot effectively protect a client secret that 
      is installed with each client (implicit grant). The security of communications with a two-party partner 
      service, on the other hand, is dependent on the effectiveness of that service's security procedures
      (client credential grant).</t>
      <t>  The security of communications with a three party service, involving a 
      registered server, a client/gadget and the OpenSocial Container, should follow the security guidelines 
      outlined in the OAuth 2.0 security considerations document (authorization grant).</t>
      <t>OpenSocial Containers SHOULD provide an ability to scope the authorization to data as narrowly as 
      possible (e.g., allow reading but not writing if a client only performs reads).</t> 
      <xref target="Issue-1138">Discussion</xref>
    </section>
   <section title="Access Token Scopes and Expiration Times">
      <t>OpenSocial Containers SHOULD issue access tokens with short expiration times to limit the scope 
      of security breaches due to stolen access tokens.  The token expiration policy is left to the 
      specific implementation and may vary depending on the client requesting the token.  
      Expiration times of 1 hour or less, and tokens with limited scope may be used with less 
      trusted clients while expiration times of several hours and tokens with increased scope may be 
      used for more trusted clients.  An OpenSocial Container SHOULD document (at least for administrators)
      how to configure token scopes and expiration times if these values are configurable.</t>
    </section>
    
     <section title="Gadget Request Context">
        <t>Each API call from a gadget to the Core Gadget Server has a request context that usually includes
           authentication and authorization information. Typically, the context
           information includes the requester id (the user initiating the request) and
           app Id (the application, or whatever is acting as the user's agent). It may
           include other core container-specific information.  The requesting application
           and user may be implied through the OAuth tokens, or may be provided explicitly
           in the xoauth_requestor_id optional parameter.  Request contexts can also
           include things such as cookies, URI parmaters, client SSL certificates and
           other information.</t>
      </section>   
          
      <section title="Anonymous access to data">
        <t>An OpenSocial Container may accept
        requests with no authentication or authorization information
        for public data. A container may provide a public version (e.g., of a
        profile) if no authorization information is provided.</t>
        <t>Note that the data provided for a given RESTful URI MAY vary per
        requestor or application. The data returned from a resource URI is "the
        view of the information available to the current requestor/application combination".</t> 
       </section>
       
       <section title="Data Access Return Codes">
        <t>In the case where no information is available due to lack of authorization,
        an HTTP 401 Unauthorized response SHOULD be returned to the client. In the
        case where at least some view of the information is available, it SHOULD be
        returned using a 200 status, with a standard OAuth WWW-Authenticate: header
        indicating that additional information may be available when using a
        different authorization context.</t>
      </section>
   
  </section>
 
  
     <section title="Content Upload" anchor="Content-Upload">
    <section title="Two Step Upload"
             anchor="twoStepUpload">
     <xref target="Issue-1211">Discussion</xref>
     <t>Content Upload is a generic mechanism to allow for a standard way to
     upload content.  This mechanism MAY be used to upload to an
     existing Album, MediaItem endpoint, or where appropriate. In most scenarios an uploaded
     content is associated with creation of an entity. Upload of content
     routinely causes the creation of the entity. For example, uploading a
     photo causes the container to create a new media item. The application can
     then update that MediaItem and set attributes via a second request at some
     later time. The requests look like: 
     <list>
      <t>Step 1: Upload Photo</t>
      <t>Step 2: Update Photo attributes (title, description, etc.)</t>
     </list>The two step request process is illustrated below.</t>
     <t>Step 1: Upload the image in the album. 
     <figure>
      <preamble>Request</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
POST /album/112233?mediaType=IMAGE HTTP/1.1
&lt;usual headers&gt;
Accept-Type: application/xml
Content-Type: image/gif
Content-Length: length
GIF89a....&lt;binary data&gt;
</artwork>
     </figure>
     <figure>
      <preamble>Response</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
&lt;feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:ossearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/"&gt;
  &lt;author&gt;&lt;uri&gt;urn:guid:example.org:33445577722&lt;/uri&gt;&lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;link rel="next" href="http://api.example.org/..." /&gt;
  &lt;entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:osapi="http://opensocial.org/2008/opensocialapi"&gt;
    &lt;content type="application/xml"&gt;
      &lt;mediaitem xmlns="http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial"&gt;
        &lt;id&gt;223344&lt;/id&gt;
        &lt;type&gt;IMAGE&lt;/type&gt;
      &lt;/mediaitem&gt;
    &lt;/content&gt;
    &lt;title /&gt;
    &lt;updated&gt;2008-10-24T20:30:40.500Z&lt;/updated&gt;
    &lt;author /&gt;
  &lt;/entry&gt;
&lt;/feed&gt;
</artwork>
     </figure></t>
     <t>Step 2: PUT MediaItem details to MediaItem (id:223344) </t>
	 <t>Note: response includes "caption" in addition to "title".  
	 Caption is being deprecated in the 1.0 data format and will be removed
	 entirely in a future version of the spec.
     <figure>
      <preamble>Request</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
&lt;entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:osapi="http://opensocial.org/2008/opensocialapi"&gt;
  &lt;content type="application/xml"&gt;
    &lt;mediaitem xmlns="http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial"&gt;
        &lt;id&gt;223344&lt;/id&gt;
        &lt;type&gt;IMAGE&lt;/type&gt;
        &lt;url&gt;http://cdn.example.org/223344.gif&lt;/url&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Lena&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/mediaitem&gt;
  &lt;/content&gt;
  &lt;title /&gt;
  &lt;updated&gt;2008-10-24T20:30:40.500Z&lt;/updated&gt;
  &lt;author /&gt;
&lt;/entry&gt;       
      
</artwork>
     </figure>
     <figure>
      <preamble>Response</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
&lt;feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:ossearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/"&gt;
  &lt;author&gt;&lt;uri&gt;urn:guid:example.org:33445577722&lt;/uri&gt;&lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;link rel="next" href="http://api.example.org/..." /&gt;
  &lt;ossearch:totalResults&gt;100&lt;/ossearch:totalResults&gt;
  &lt;ossearch:startIndex&gt;1&lt;/ossearch:startIndex&gt;
  &lt;ossearch:itemsPerPage&gt;10&lt;/ossearch:itemsPerPage&gt;
  &lt;entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:osapi="http://opensocial.org/2008/opensocialapi"&gt;
    &lt;content type="application/xml"&gt;
      &lt;mediaitem xmlns="http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial"&gt;
        &lt;id&gt;223344&lt;/id&gt;
        &lt;type&gt;IMAGE&lt;/type&gt;
        &lt;url&gt;http://cdn.example.org/223344.gif&lt;/url&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Lena&lt;/title&gt;
      &lt;/mediaitem&gt;
    &lt;/content&gt;
    &lt;title /&gt;
    &lt;updated&gt;2008-10-24T20:30:40.500Z&lt;/updated&gt;
    &lt;author /&gt;
  &lt;/entry&gt;
&lt;/feed&gt;
</artwork>
     </figure>The response indicates that the media item was updated.</t>
     
    </section>
    <section title="Shortcut Upload Method">
     <t>The shortcut upload mechanism is OPTIONAL. This two step process shown
     above can be merged into one by a single POST request with the content
     type set to the item being uploaded. The POST URL can optionally pass the
     attributes. The Accept-type indicates the format of the response expected.
     
     <figure>
      <preamble>Request</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
POST /album/112233/mediaitem/?title=Lena&amp;type=IMAGE HTTP/1.1
&lt;usual headers&gt;
Accept-Type: application/json
Content-Type: image/gif
Content-Length: length
GIF89a....&lt;binary data&gt;        
</artwork>
     </figure>
     <figure>
      <preamble>Response</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
{
  "startIndex" : 1,
  "itemsPerPage" : 1,
  "totalResults" : 1,
  "entry" : {
    "id" : "223344",
    "title" : "Lena",
    "type" : "IMAGE",
  }
}        
</artwork>
     </figure></t>
    </section>
  <section title="Multi-part Uploads">
   <t>A container MAY choose to support file uploads from browsers to the RPC
   endpoint and have the uploaded files be passed as parameters to the RPC.
   This is achieved by browsers posting a form which contains the files to the
   endpoint and including a form-parameter called "request" which contains the
   form-encoded RPC request. The form input element names for the uploaded
   files will be bound to the corresponding parameter names on execution.</t>

    <t>A multipart form-data request mechanism ("Content-Type:
    multipart/form-data") enables upload of content. Such a request has the
    POST body segmented into several sections (fields) with each field
    identified by a name. The field name "request" is reserved and contains
    request operation details (same as the contents on the POST body in the
    vanilla POST operation).</t>
    <t>The fields with any other name contain content to be uploaded to the
    OpenSocial container. To allow batching and multiple file uploads in a
    single call, multiple fields (identified with unique field names) are
    allowed. The OpenSocial request can refer to the content being uploaded by
    setting the URL to "@field:&lt;fieldname&gt;". The container may host the
    uploaded file and replace the URL field with a fully qualified URL for
    future access.</t>
    <t>For a successful upload, the response code of the request will be
    associated with the response code of the action request on the resource.
    However, in case of a failure due to a file size exceeding limits, an error
    code of 413 ("Request Entity Too Large") MUST be returned. The requested
    action associated with the file upload MUST NOT be executed.</t>
    <t>
     <figure>
      <preamble>Example:</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
&lt;usual headers&gt;
Content-type: multipart/form-data; boundary=------------abcdef012345xyZ
Content-length: &lt;contentLength&gt;
------------abcdef012345xyZ
Content-Disposition: form-data; name="request"
[{
  "method":"activities.create",
  "params": {
    "userId":["@viewer"],
    "groupId":"@self",
    "appId":"@app",
    "activity": {
      "title": "hello world!",
      "mediaItems": [ {
        "mimeType":"image",
        "url":"@field:image1"
      } ]
    }
  },
  "id":"key"
}
------------abcdef012345xyZ
Content-Disposition: form-data; name="image1"
GIF89....&lt;image data&gt;
------------abcdef012345xyZ
</artwork>
     </figure>
    </t>
   </section>
   </section>

  <section title="Common Elements">
    <section title="Request-ID" anchor="Request-ID">
     <t>A string identifying a request.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Auth-Token" anchor="Auth-Token">
     <t>A string used to authenticate a request.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Content-Type" anchor="Content-Type">
     <t>A string used to identify the type of content in a request or response.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Return-Object" anchor="Return-Object">
     <t>The actual content included in the response. Each service method defines the object that is included as the Return-Object.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Invalidation-Key-List" anchor="Invalidation-Key-List">
     <t>A collection of keys that identify resources that should have their cached version refreshed.  Keys can either be URLs or IDs of objects to be refreshed.</t>

    <t>Keys that refer to URLs MUST include a protocol prefix (e.g. 'http://') so
    they can be distinguished from ids. Each request accepts a repeated group
    of keys.</t> 

     <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:highlight>Invalidation-Key-List</x:highlight> = "{"
                           &lt;"&gt; "invalidationKeys" &lt;"&gt; ":" "[" #Invalidation-Key "]"
                        "}"
<x:highlight>Invalidation-Key</x:highlight> = &lt;any valid URL&gt; / <eref target="./Core-Data.xml#Object-Id">Object-Id</eref>                    
</artwork>

    </section>
    <section title="HTTP-Status-Code">
   <texttable>
    <ttcol align="left">Status Code</ttcol>
    <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
    <c>400 BAD REQUEST</c>
    <c align="left">OpenSocial application servers MUST return 400 BAD REQUEST
    under any one or more of the following conditions: 
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Invalid request URI</t>
     <t>Invalid HTTP Header</t>
     <t>Receiving an unsupported, nonstandard parameter</t>
     <t>A parameter is repeated</t>
     <t>Receiving an invalid HTTP Message Body</t>
    </list></c>
    <c>401 UNAUTHORIZED</c>
    <c align="left">OpenSocial container servers MUST return 401 UNAUTHORIZED
    when receiving a request for a protected resource and the request is either
    
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Missing OAuth authorization credentials as described in 
     <xref target="OAuth-Consumer-Request-1.0-Draft-1" /> for OAuth 1.0a or in <xref target='draft-ietf-oauth-v2-22'/> for OAuth 2.0 requests.</t>
     <t>OAuth authorization credentials are present, but the user identity is
     not authorized to access the protected resource. If the request already
     included authorization credentials, the 401 response indicates that the
     request has been refused for those credentials. A 401 response MUST
     include a WWW-Authenticate header field indicating the request MAY present
     an OAuth token for the container server's realm. Example:
     WWW-Authenticate: OAuth realm="http://sp.example.com/"</t>
    </list></c>
    <c>403 FORBIDDEN</c>
    <c align="left">The server understood the request but is refusing to
    fulfill it. Authorization will not help. The current authorization context
    does not allow the request.</c>
    <c>404 NOT FOUND</c>
    <c align="left">The server has not found a resource (such as a feed or
    entry) that matches the request URI.</c>
    <c>405 METHOD NOT ALLOWED</c>
    <c align="left">The method specified in the Request-Line is not allowed for
    the resource identified by the Request-URI. The response MUST include an
    Allow header containing a list of valid methods for the requested
    resource.</c>
    <c>409 CONFLICT</c>
    <c>The request could not be completed due to a conflict with the current
    state of the resource. This code is only allowed in situations where it is
    expected that the user might be able to resolve the conflict and resubmit
    the request. The response body SHOULD include enough information for the
    user to recognize the source of the conflict. Ideally, the response entity
    would include enough information for the user or user agent to fix the
    problem; however, that might not be possible and is not required. Conflicts
    are most likely to occur in response to a PUT request. For example, this
    code can be used for a limit exceeded error as well as conflicting updates.
    See the error message for more information.</c>
    <c>500 INTERNAL SERVER ERROR</c>
    <c align="left">Internal error. This is the default code that is used for
    all unrecognized errors.</c>
    <c>501 NOT IMPLEMENTED</c>
    <c align="left">The request was valid but has not been implemented by the
    provider. A container SHOULD return 501 NOT IMPLEMENTED when receiving a
    request for an OPTIONAL/MAY feature that the container does not
    implement.</c>
   </texttable>
      
    </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Request Parameters">
   <section title="Standard Request Parameters"
            anchor="Standard-Request-Parameters">
    <t>All requests MUST support the following parameters:</t>
    <section title="Updated Since" anchor="Request-Parameter-UpdatedSince-Value">
     <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-UpdatedSince-Value</x:highlight> = <xref target="XSdateTime" /></artwork>
     <t>When specified the container should only return
     items whose updated date &amp; time is equal to or more recent then the
     specified value. The value MUST be a valid 
     <xref target="XSdateTime" /> (e.g. 2008-01-23T04:56:22Z).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Format" anchor="Request-Parameter-Format-Value">
      <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-Formet-Value</x:highlight> = "json" / "xml" / "atom"</artwork>
      <t>Specifies the desired return encoding of the request.
     Must be one of "json", "xml", or "atom".</t>
    </section>

   </section>
   <section title="Collection Request Parameters" anchor="Collection-Request-Parameters">
    <t>All requests that return a Collection of objects MUST support the following parameters:</t>
    <section title="Count" anchor="Request-Parameter-Count-Value">
      <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-Count-Value</x:highlight> = number</artwork>
      <t>The page size for a paged collection. If no parameter
       is specified the container can choose how many items in the collection
       should be returned. However, the container SHOULD support a large default
       count value so that all items can be returned by default.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Filter By" anchor="Request-Parameter-FilterBy-Value">
      <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-FilterBy-Value</x:highlight> = string</artwork>
      <t>For a collection, return entries filtered by the
     given field name.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Filter Operation" anchor="Request-Parameter-FilterOp-Value">
      <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-FilterOp-Value</x:highlight> = "contains" / "equals" / "startsWith" / "present"</artwork>
      <t>The operation to use when filtering a collection by
     a field specified in 'filterBy', defaults to "contains". Valid values: 
     <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="contains">Return elements where filterValue appears
      somewhere in the element's filterBy field value.</t>
      <t hangText="equals">Return elements where filterValue exactly matches
      the element's filterBy field value.</t>
      <t hangText="startsWith">Return elements where filterValue exactly
      matches the first N characters of the element's filterBy field value,
      where N is the length of the filterValue string.</t>
      <t hangText="present">Return elements where the element's filterBy field
      value is not empty or null.</t>
     </list></t>
    </section>
    <section title="Filter Value" anchor="Request-Parameter-FilterValue-Value">
      <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-FilterValue-Value</x:highlight> = string</artwork>
      <t>The value to use when filtering a collection. For example: </t>
      <artwork type="example"
         xml:space="preserve">
{ ... "filterBy" : "name", "filterOp" : "startsWith", "filterValue" : "John" ... }
</artwork>
      <t>returns all items whose name field starts with John. Johnny and John
      Doe would both be included.)</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Sort Order" anchor="Request-Parameter-SortOrder-Value">
      <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-SortOrder-Value</x:highlight> = "ascending" / "descending"</artwork>
      <t>Can either be 'ascending' or 'descending',
     defaults to ascending. Used to sort objects in a collection.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Start Index" anchor="Request-Parameter-StartIndex-Value">
      <artwork type="abnf"><x:highlight>Request-Parameter-StartIndex-Value</x:highlight> = number</artwork>
      <t>Index into a paged collection.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Examples">
     <figure>
      <preamble>Behavior of query parameters to determine if two people are
     friends (important part is the query string):</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
/people/@me/@self?filterBy=@friends&amp;filterOp=contains&amp;filterValue=&lt;someUserId&gt;
</artwork>
     </figure>
     <t>This will return nothing if the other ID is not a friend, the
    current user if the two are friends. filterValue may take a specific person
    identifier of @owner or @viewer.</t>
     <figure>
      <preamble>To determine the mutual friends between two people (important
     part is the query string):</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">
/people/@me/@friends?filterBy=@friends&amp;filterOp=contains&amp;filterValue=&lt;someUserId&gt;
</artwork>
     </figure>
     <t>This will return the set of mutual friends between the current
    user and someUserId. filterValue may take a specific person identifier of
    @owner or @viewer.</t>
     <t>Note: The container is not required to support all values for filtering,
    sorting and getting the last set of updated items from a collection. If the
    container does not respect the filer, sort or updatedSince param the
    response should contain "filtered : false", "sorted : false", or
    "updatedSince : false".</t>
    </section>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Discovery" anchor="Discovery">
   <t>A container declares what collection and features it supports, and
   provides templates for discovering them, via a simple discovery document. A
   client starts the discovery process at the container's identifier URI (e.g.,
   example.org). The full flow is available at http://xrds-simple.net/core/1.0/;
   in a nutshell: 
   <list style="numbers">
    <t>Client GETs {container-url} with Accept: application/xrds+xml</t>
    <t>Container responds with either an X-XRDS-Location: header pointing to
    the discovery document, or the document itself.</t>
    <t>If the client received an X-XRDS-Location: header, follow it to get the
    discovery document.</t>
   </list>Once the client has the XRDS document, they have the complete set of
   services supported by that service. All OpenSocial service types declare the
   base URI in the XRDS URI element. Each service type declares the root URI
   for the service. Service specific parameters are passed to each endpoint
   using a fixed URI format. This format is defined by each service. The
   discovery document is an XML file in the same format used for OpenID and
   OAuth discovery, defined at http://xrds-simple.net/core/1.0/: 
   <figure>
    <artwork xml:space="preserve">
&lt;XRDS xmlns="xri://$xrds"&gt;
   &lt;XRD xmlns:simple="http://xrds-simple.net/core/1.0" xmlns="xri://$XRD*($v*2.0)" version="2.0"&gt;
       &lt;Type&gt;xri://$xrds*simple&lt;/Type&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
         &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/people&lt;/Type&gt;
         &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/people&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
         &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/groups&lt;/Type&gt;
         &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/groups&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
         &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/activities&lt;/Type&gt;
         &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/activities&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
         &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org//2008/opensocial/appData&lt;/Type&gt;
         &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/appData&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
         &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/cache/invalidate&lt;/Type&gt;
         &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/cache/invalidate&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
         &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/messages&lt;/Type&gt;
         &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/messages&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
          &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/albums&lt;/Type&gt;
          &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/albums&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
       &lt;Service&gt;
          &lt;Type&gt;http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/mediaItems&lt;/Type&gt;
          &lt;URI&gt;http://api.example.org/mediaItems&lt;/URI&gt;
       &lt;/Service&gt;
   &lt;/XRD&gt;
&lt;/XRDS&gt;         
</artwork>
   </figure></t>
   <t>Each Service advertises a service provided by the container. Each
   container MUST support the service Types documented below and MAY support
   others by advertising them in the discovery document. Each service comprises
   a set of resources defined by the given URI Template (or URI, if there is
   only a single resource). Clients follow the URIs and instantiate the
   templates to find and operate on specific resources. (URI Template syntax is
   documented at
   http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-gregorio-uritemplate-03.txt.)</t>
   <t>The set of substitution variables is fixed for each service Type. The
   core set of service Types and their substitution variables is documented
   below. Extensions to OpenSocial SHOULD document their substitution
   variables; note that a reasonable place to put human readable documentation
   is at the namespace URI.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Services"
           anchor="services">
   <section title="Cache"
            anchor="Cache-Service">
      <t>The cache service is used to manage the resources cached by the container for a given application.</t>
    <section title="Invalidate" anchor="Cache-Service-Invalidate">

     <t>An application can execute an invalidation request as a POST to the Cache service. Requests include a list of URLs associated with resources that should have their cache invalidated.  Invalidation keys can include the URL of the gadget spec, associated message bundle files, static resources (e.g. images, CSS), or remote content fetched via <eref target="./Core-Gadget.xml#osapi.http">osapi.http</eref>.</t>
    <t>Containers MUST support the invalidation endpoint even if they do not
    perform any caching and MUST provide an entry for it in their XRDS. To
    invalidate content a developer's backend notifies the container of the
    content it wishes to invalidate by making a 2-legged OAuth call to the
    Cache service with one or many keys to be invalidated. The consumer key
    in the 2-legged OAuth call is used by the container to identify the calling
    application.</t>

     <t>Containers MAY reject invalidation requests for policy reasons. Containers MAY continue to serve content that has already been invalidated until the container is able to successfully fetch a replacement from it original source.</t>
     <t>Response codes have the following meanings:</t>
      <list style="symbols">
       <t>200 - Success, all invalidations processed successfully.</t>
       <t>403 - Forbidden because authentication failed.</t>
       <t>409 - The request was partially processed, the set of invalidation keys that were not honored MUST be included in the response body in the format the request was made.</t>
     </list>
     <t>XRDS Type: http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial/cache/invalidate</t>
     <t>Requests and responses for the Cache service's Invalidate method use the following values:</t>
     <artwork type="abnf"
         xml:space="preserve">
<x:ref>REST-HTTP-Method</x:ref>        = "POST"
<x:ref>REST-Request-URI</x:ref>        = "/cache/invalidate"
<x:ref>REST-Request-Parameters</x:ref> = null 
<x:ref>REST-Request-Payload</x:ref>    = <x:ref>Invalidation-Key-List</x:ref>
<x:ref>RPC-Method</x:ref>              = "cache.invalidate"
<x:ref>RPC-Request-Parameters</x:ref>  = <x:ref>Invalidation-Key-List</x:ref>
<x:ref>Return-Object</x:ref>           = [ <x:ref>Invalidation-Key-List</x:ref> ]
     </artwork>
     <t>Here is an example that invalidates the cache for the gadget spec and message bundle of an application using REST:</t>
     <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
POST /api/rest/cache/invalidate HTTP/1.1
Host: api.example.org
Authorization: hh5s93j4hdidpola
Content-Type: application/json
{
  "invalidationKeys" : [ 
      "http://www.myapp.com/gadgetspec.xml", 
      "http://www.myapp.com/messagebundle.xml"
  ]
}
</artwork>
    <t>Here is an example illustrates how information for users and a static
    resources can be invalidated using RPC. The example shows how
    to specify a user with a global ID (i.e. an ID which includes the domain of the
    container) or a relative ID. The static resource in this example is the
    gadget spec itself.</t>
      <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
POST /api/rpc
Host: api.example.org
Content-Type: application/json
{
   "method" : "cache.invalidate",
   "params" : {
       "invalidationKeys" : [ 
           "example.org:12345", 
           "example.org:4567", 
           "3456778", 
           "http://www.myapp.com/gadgetpec.xml"
       ]
   }
}
</artwork>
    </section>
   </section>
   <section title="System"
            anchor="System-Service">
    <t>The System service is used to introspect the API server for the set of
    available services and operations and for metadata about those
    services.  The System service only supports the RPC protocol.</t>
    <section title="ListMethods" anchor="System-Service-ListMethods">
     <t>Containers MUST implement this operation which takes no parameters and
     returns an array of all methods supported by the endpoint including the
     system methods.</t>
     <t>Requests and responses to the System service's List Methods method use the following values:</t>
     <artwork type="abnf" xml:space="preserve">
<x:ref>RPC-Method</x:ref>             = "system.listMethods"
<x:ref>RPC-Request-Parameters</x:ref> = null
<x:ref>Return-Object</x:ref>          = [ #String ]
</artwork>
     <t>Here's an example using RPC:</t>
      <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
POST /api/rpc
Host: api.example.org
Content-Type: application/json
{
   "method" : "system.listMethods",
   "params" : {}
}
</artwork>     
     <t>A container which only supports read access to people
     and read and create access for activities would include the following Return-Object in the response:</t>
      <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
[
  "people.get", 
  "activities.get", 
  "activities.create",  
  "system.listMethods",
  "system.methodSignatures", 
  "system.methodHelp"
]</artwork>
    </section>
    <section title="MethodSignatures" anchor="System-Service-MethodSignatures">
     <t>Containers MUST implement this operation that returns a method
     signature describing the types of the parameters, their default values and
     the type of the return value for a given operation. Note that this scheme
     does not match that used for XML-RPC definition of method signatures which
     only specifies a mapping for positional parameters. Type definitions used
     here match the scheme used in the OpenSocial Javascript API.</t>
     <artwork type="abnf" xml:space="preserve">
<x:ref>RPC-Method</x:ref>             = "system.methodSignatures"
<x:ref>RPC-Request-Parameters</x:ref> = { &lt;"&gt; "methodName" &lt;"&gt; ":" String "}"
<x:ref>Return-Object</x:ref>          = Method-Signatures
<x:highlight>Method-Signatures</x:highlight>      = "{"
                             &lt;"&gt; "return" &lt;"&gt; ":" ( String-Value / String-List ) ","
                             #Parameter-Spec
                         "}"
<x:highlight>Parameter-Spec</x:highlight>         = Param-Name ":" "{"
                               &lt;"&gt; "type" &lt;"&gt; ":" ( String-Value / String-List ) ","
                             [ &lt;"&gt; "default" &lt;"&gt; ":" ( "null" / String-Value / String-List ) "," ]
                             [ &lt;"&gt; "required" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;"&gt; false &lt;"&gt; ]
                         "}"
<x:highlight>Param-Name</x:highlight>             = String-Value                         
<x:highlight>String-Value</x:highlight>           = &lt;"&gt; String &lt;"&gt;
<x:highlight>String-List</x:highlight>            = "[" #String-Value "]"
                      
</artwork>
     <t>The "return" field indicates the type of the result. If the
     service can return more than one type then the value is an array of the
     possible return types. Each named field in the response maps to a
     parameter of the operation and contains information about the types and
     values accepted for that parameter. The existence of "default" in the
     parameter detail indicates the parameter has a default value. The value of
     a default may be null which means that its not introspectable and usually
     means that it is some complex derivation. Parameters are assumed to be
     required unless otherwise indicated by the existence of the "required"
     field with a value of false.</t>
    <t>Here is an example of a request for the method signature of <eref target="./Social-API-Server.xml#People-Service-Get">people.get</eref>.</t>
    <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
POST /api/rpc
Host: api.example.org
Content-Type: application/json
{
   "method" : "system.methodSignatures",
   "params" : { "methodName" : "people.get" }
}
</artwork>
    <t>Here is the response to a request for the method signature of <eref target="./Social-API-Server.xml#People-Service-Get">people.get</eref>.</t>
      <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
{
  "return" : ["opensocial.Person", "Array.&lt;opensocial.Person&gt;"],
  "auth" : {
     "default" : null,
     "type" : "AuthToken"
   },
   "userId" : {
     "default" : "@me",
     "type" : ["String", "Array.&lt;String&gt;"]
   },
   "groupId" : {
     "default" : "@self",
     "type" : "String"
   },
   "fields" : {
     "default" : ["id","name","thumbnailUrl","profileUrl"],
     "type" : "Array.&lt;String&gt;"
   },
   "count" : {
     "type" : "int",
     "required" : false
   },
   "startIndex" : {
     "type" : "int",
     "required" : false
   }
}
</artwork>
    </section>
    <section title="MethodHelp"
             anchor="System-Service-MethodHelp">
     <t>Containers MAY implement this operation that returns a textual
     description of the operation identified by the methodName parameter. A
     container can choose to return either plaintext or HTML as the
     response.</t>
     <artwork type="abnf" xml:space="preserve">
<x:ref>RPC-Method</x:ref>             = "system.methodHelp"
<x:ref>RPC-Request-Parameters</x:ref> = { &lt;"&gt; "methodName" &lt;"&gt; ":" &lt;"&gt; String &lt;"&gt; "}"
<x:ref>Return-Object</x:ref>          = String
</artwork>
     <t>Here's a request to get the help content for the people.get method.</t>
          <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
POST /api/rpc
Host: api.example.org
Content-Type: application/json
{
   "method" : "system.methodSignatures",
   "params" : { "methodName" : "people.get" }
}
</artwork>
     <t>The response might be something like:</t>
          <artwork type="example" xml:space="preserve">
Used to fetch profile information about people.
</artwork>
    </section>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Concurrency Control">
   <t>OpenSocial containers MAY support concurrency control to 
   prevent multiple clients from overwriting each other's data. The mechanism supported by OpenSocial uses the
   standard HTTP/AtomPub optimistic concurrency mechanism based on ETags (see
   section 9.5 of 
   <xref target="RFC5023" /> for details; the same mechanism applies regardless
   of the data format used for the body of the PUT).</t>
   <section title="Discovery">
    <t>Concurrency control is available on a resource-by-resource basis. When
    an updateable resource supports concurrency control, the container SHOULD
    supply an ETag encoding the resource's current state when supplying a
    representation to clients. If a resource does not support optimistic
    concurrency, it MUST respond to an update request containing an If-Match:
    header with a 403 Not Implemented error.</t>
    <t>A server which chooses not to support optimistic concurrency SHOULD omit
    ETags on its responses for updateable resources. A client SHOULD assume
    that optimistic concurrency is not available if no ETag is present.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Semantics">
    <t>When a client is given an ETag, it MAY supply that ETag in an If-Match:
    header on subsequent updates. The semantics are that the client can supply
    the new representation and the previous ETag; the server inspects the
    current state of the resource and applies the update if the client supplied
    ETag matches (meaning no intervening updates have happened), otherwise
    responds with a 409 Conflict error and the new ETag. Clients may then take
    appropriate actions to resolve the conflict, or fail the operation,
    depending on their needs. Clients are also free to use PUT to simply
    overwrite a resource with a new state at any time, ignoring possible
    overwriting problems.</t>
    <t>If partial updates are supported (see below), a server MUST accept an
    ETag given for either a base resource or a projection of that resource upon
    a subsequent PUT for that resource. That is, it is legal to supply an ETag
    you received when GETting the full representation of a resource even if you
    are only PUTting back a single field. If you intend to simply overwrite
    that single field, then you skip sending any ETag.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Partial Updates">
    <t>Partial updates avoid the need to send full representations of data on
    updates, especially for People and App Data. The primary use case is when a
    client has retrieved a full representation and subsequently wishes to send
    a small update to a server. In the most general case, the client may have a
    series of small updates (e.g., changing tags on a large number of contacts)
    scattered across many resources. To accomplish these partial updates we
    will take advantage of the "fields" parameter.</t>
    <t>When the "fields" parameter is specified on a url, only those fields
    will be looked at when updating an object. If a field is in the parameter
    list but not part of the post, that would be considered a removal of that
    field. If the field is in the post but not in the parameter list a 400 bad
    request error will be returned. If a field is in both places then it will
    be updated normally.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Example">
    <t>This example demonstrates the use of etags to detect an incompatible
    update to the profile of the user identified in the auth token. The request
    is attempting to update the 'books' field and passes the etag the client
    received when it retrieved the person object prior to update. The etag is
    added to the update request shown below but an intervening update from
    another client has made the change incompatible and so the update is
    rejected.</t>
    <t>Notes: 
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>The error code 409 is the HTTP Conflict status code.</t>
     <t>The error object "data" field contains a limited representation of the
     latest version of the person object including an up-to-date etag value.
     Containers MAY omit this data from conflict error responses.</t>
    </list>
    <figure>
     <artwork xml:space="preserve">
POST /rpc HTTP/1.1
Host: api.example.org
Authorization: &lt;auth token&gt;
Content-Type: application/json
{
    "method" : "person.update",
    "id" : "setMyData"
    "params: {
      "userId" : "@me",
      "groupId" : "@self",
      "person" : {
        "etag" : "767ffdef7",
        "books" : ["The Prince", "Hotel New Hampshire"]
      }
    }
}
HTTP/1.x 207 Multi-Status
Content-Type: application/json
{
   "id" : "myself",
   "error" : {
     "code" : 409
     "message" : "Conflict detected",
     "data" : {
       "etag" : "8543de12",
       "books" : ["The Right Stuff", "About a boy"]
     }
   }
}
</artwork>
    </figure></t>
   </section>
  </section>
 </middle>
 <back>
   <references title="Discussion">
  <!-- Spec change issues/discussion -->
   <reference anchor='Issue-1142'
              target="http://code.google.com/p/opensocial-resources/issues/detail?id=1142">
    <front>
     <title>Fix Gadget XSD</title>
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='Issue-1138'
              target="http://code.google.com/p/opensocial-resources/issues/detail?id=1138">
    <front>
     <title>OAuth 2.0 Support</title>
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='Issue-1211'
              target="http://code.google.com/p/opensocial-resources/issues/detail?id=1211">
    <front>
     <title>Content Upload spec consistency check/cleanup</title>
    </front>
   </reference>
  </references>
  <references>
   <reference anchor='RFC20'>
    <front>
     <title>ASCII format for Network Interchange</title>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='20' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
    <front>
     <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
     <author initials='S.'
             surname='Bradner'
             fullname='Scott Bradner'>
      <organization abbrev='HarvardU'>Harvard University</organization>
     </author>
     <date month='March'
           year='1997' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC2234'>
    <front>
     <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='2234' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC2606'>
    <front>
     <title>Reserved Top Level DNS Names</title>
     <author initials='D.'
             surname='Eastlake'
             fullname='Donald E. Eastlake 3rd'>
      <organization abbrev='IBM'>IBM</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='A.'
             surname='Panitz'
             fullname='Aliza R. Panitz'></author>
     <date month='June'
           year='1999' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='2606' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC2616'>
    <front>
     <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</title>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='2616' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC3986'>
    <front>
     <title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='3986' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC4287'>
    <front>
     <title>The Atom Syndication Format</title>
     <author initials='M.'
             surname='Nottingham'
             fullname='Mark Nottingham'></author>
     <author initials='R.'
             surname='Sayre'
             fullname='Robert Sayre'></author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2005' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='4287' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC4627'>
    <front>
     <title>The application/json Media Type for JavaScript Object Notation (JSON)
</title>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='4627' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC5023'>
    <front>
     <title>The Atom Publishing Protocol</title>
     <author initials='J.'
             surname='Gregorio'
             fullname='Joe Gregorio'>
      <organization abbrev='GOOG'>Google</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='B.'
             surname='de hOra'
             fullname='Bill de hOra'>
      <organization>NewBay Software</organization>
     </author>
     <date month='October'
           year='2007' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='5023' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Rison"
              target="http://mjtemplate.org/examples/rison.html">
    <front>
     <title>Rison - Compact Data in URIs</title>
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="XSdateTime"
              target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#dateTime">
    <front>
     <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second Edition</title>
     <author initials='P.V.'
             surname='Biron'
             fullname='Paul V. Biron'>
      <organization>Kaiser Permanente, for Health Level Seven</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='A.'
             surname='Malhotra'
             fullname='Ashok Malhotra'>
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
     </author>
     <date month='October'
           year='2004' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="JSON-RPC"
              target="http://groups.google.com/group/json-rpc/web/json-rpc-1-2-proposal?pli=1">
    <front>
     <title>JSON-RPC 2.0 Specification proposal</title>
     <author surname='JSON-RPC Working Group'
             fullname='JSON-RPC Working Group &lt;json-rpc(at)googlegroups.com&gt;'>
             </author>
     <date month='November'
           year='2008' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="XML-RPC-Introspection"
              target="http://xmlrpc-c.sourceforge.net/introspection.html">
    <front>
     <title>XML-RPC Introspection</title>
     <author surname='opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com'
             fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group'></author>
     <date month='January'
           year='2000' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='OAuth-Core-1.0'
              target='http://oauth.net/core/1.0/'>
    <front>
     <title>OAuth Core 1.0</title>
     <author initials='M.'
             surname='Atwood'
             fullname='Mark Atwood'></author>
     <author initials='R. M.'
             surname='Conlan'
             fullname='Richard M. Conlan'>
      <organization>Google</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='B.'
             surname='Cook'
             fullname='Blaine Cook'>
      <organization>Twitter</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='L.'
             surname='Culver'
             fullname='Leah Culver'>
      <organization>Pownce</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='K.'
             surname='Elliott-McCrea'
             fullname='Kellan Elliott-McCrea'>
      <organization>Flickr</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='L.'
             surname='Halff'
             fullname='Larry Halff'>
      <organization>ma.gnolia</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='E.'
             surname='Hammer-Lahav'
             fullname='Eran Hammer-Lahav'></author>
     <author initials='B.'
             surname='Laurie'
             fullname='Ben Laurie'>
      <organization>Google</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='C.'
             surname='Messina'
             fullname='Chris Messina'></author>
     <author initials='J.'
             surname='Panzer'
             fullname='John Panzer'></author>
     <author initials='S.'
             surname='Quigley'
             fullname='Sam Quigley'>
      <organization>Twitter</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='D.'
             surname='Recordon'
             fullname='David Recordon'>
      <organization>six apart</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='E.'
             surname='Sandler'
             fullname='Eran Sandler'>
      <organization>Yedda</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='J.'
             surname='Sergent'
             fullname='Jonathan Sergent'>
      <organization>ma.gnolia</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='B.'
             surname='Slesinsky'
             fullname='Brian Slesinsky'></author>
     <author initials='A.'
             surname='Smith'
             fullname='Andy Smith'>
      <organization>Jaiku</organization>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2007' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="OAuth-Consumer-Request-1.0-Draft-1"
              target="http://oauth.googlecode.com/svn/spec/ext/consumer_request/1.0/drafts/1/spec.html">
    <front>
     <title>OAuth Consumer Request 1.0 Draft 1</title>
     <author initials='E.'
             surname='Hammer-Lahav'
             fullname='Eran Hammer-Lahav'></author>
             <date month='December'
             year='2007' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   
    
   <reference anchor="draft-ietf-oauth-v2-22"
               target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-v2-22">
     <front>
       <title>The OAuth 2.0 Authorization Protocol</title>
       <author initials='E.'
               surname='Hammer-Lahav'
               fullname='Eran Hammer-Lahav'>
               <organization>Yahoo !</organization>
       </author>
       <author initials='D.'
               surname='Recordon'
               fullname='David'>
               <organization>Facebook</organization>
       </author>
       <author initials='D.'
               surname='Hardt'
               fullname='Dick'>
               <organization>Microsoft</organization>
       </author>
       <date month='September'
             year='2011' />
     </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Core-Data"
              target="./Core-Data.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Core Data Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='August'
           year='2011' />
    </front>
   </reference>
 
   <reference anchor="Social-Data"
              target="./Social-Data.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Social Data Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='August'
           year='2011' />
    </front>
   </reference>
  </references>
  <section title="XML format XSD"
           anchor="XML_format_XSD"><xref target="Issue-1142">Discussion</xref>
    <figure>
     <artwork xml:space="preserve">
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;xs:schema xmlns:tns="http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial"
  elementFormDefault="qualified"
  targetNamespace="http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"&gt;

  &lt;xs:element name="response"&gt;
    &lt;xs:complexType&gt;
      &lt;xs:choice&gt;      
        &lt;xs:element name="entry" type="xs:anyType" /&gt;
        &lt;xs:group ref="tns:collection" /&gt;
        &lt;xs:element name="invalidationKeys" type="tns:InvalidationKeys" /&gt;
      &lt;/xs:choice&gt;
    &lt;/xs:complexType&gt;
  &lt;/xs:element&gt;    

  &lt;xs:group name="collection"&gt;        
    &lt;xs:sequence&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="itemsPerPage" type="xs:int" /&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="startIndex" type="xs:long" /&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="totalResults" type="xs:long" /&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="filtered" type="xs:boolean" /&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="sorted" type="xs:boolean" /&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="updatedSince" type="xs:boolean" /&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="list" type="xs:anyType" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1" /&gt;
        &lt;xs:element name="entry" type="xs:anyType" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded" /&gt;
      &lt;/xs:element&gt;
    &lt;/xs:sequence&gt;
  &lt;/xs:group&gt;        

  &lt;xs:complexType name="InvalidationKeys"&gt;
    &lt;xs:sequence&gt;
      &lt;xs:element name="invalidationKey" type="xs:string" maxOccurs="unbounded" /&gt;
    &lt;/xs:sequence&gt;
  &lt;/xs:complexType&gt;

&lt;/xs:schema&gt;
</artwork>
    </figure>
  </section>
 </back>
</rfc>

  