<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./OpenSocial.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
"http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="full3978"
     docName="opensocial-specification-draft"
     xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">
 <front>
  <title abbrev="OpenSocial Specification">OpenSocial Specification (draft)</title>
  <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group'>
   <address>
    <email>opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  <date month="December"
        year="2009" />
  <area>General</area>
  <keyword>OpenSocial</keyword>
  <keyword>social networking</keyword>
  <keyword>REST</keyword>
  <keyword>XML</keyword>
  <keyword>Extensible Markup Language</keyword>
  <keyword>JSON</keyword>
  <keyword>JavaScript Object Notation</keyword>
  <keyword>Atom</keyword>
 </front>
 <middle>
  <section title="Notation and Conventions">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in 
   <xref target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>
   <t>Domain name examples use <xref target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref>.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Overview">
   <t>OpenSocial is a set of APIs for building social applications that run on
   the web. OpenSocial's goal is to make more apps available to more users, by
   providing a common API that can be used in many different contexts.
   Developers can create applications, using standard JavaScript and HTML, that
   run on social websites that have implemented the OpenSocial APIs. These
   websites, known as OpenSocial containers, allow developers to access their
   social information; in return they receive a large suite of applications for
   their users.</t>
   <t>The OpenSocial APIs expose methods for accessing information about
   people, their friends, and their data, within the context of a container.
   This means that when running an application on Orkut, you'll be interacting
   with your Orkut friends, while running the same application on MySpace lets
   you interact with your MySpace friends. For more information on the types of
   information exposed by the OpenSocial API, see the Key concepts section.</t>
   <t>This document describes the concepts and principles behind the OpenSocial
   JavaScript APIs. It is a complement to the JavaScript API Reference, which
   covers the details of specific methods and parameters. This document does
   not describe any particular implementation of the API.</t>
  </section>
    <section title="Concepts and Terminology">
    <list style="hanging">
     <t hangText="Container">The OpenSocial Container. It is typically
     represented as a web page, but alternative forms that are capable of
     displaying a gadget, such as a personal computer desktop or a mobile
     device, are also accepted.</t>
     <t hangText="Developer">The entity that has authored the gadget.</t>
     <t hangText="Friend">The term "friend" is used throughout this specification and can be
      applied to a variety of relationships between people, whether or not they are actually friends, business contacts, or related through a management hierarchy. The "friend" term can be used to describe either symmetric relationships or asymmetric relationships (such as followers, as in Twitter). Also, this term can be used to refer to a human, a system, or another entity. For example, a user may "follow" updates from a bug tracking system.</t>
     <t hangText="User">This may refer to any OpenSocial Person, though in most
     contexts it is referring to the Viewer of the gadget at runtime.</t>
     <t hangText="Content">The primary entity in a gadget that will be
     displayed to an end user. Currently only two types of Content are
     supported by OpenSocial: 
      <list style="hanging">
       <t hangText="Type HTML">Type HTML gadgets are the most prevalent, and are 
    imbued with the most rich feature set. Code is provided directly in the 
    gadget XML content section for rendering and control flow. This code simply 
    assumes that functionality is available that has been requested from 
    whatever gadget features were declared. In the case of optional-declared 
    features, a simple feature-existence API can and should be consulted to 
    ensure the capability is enabled. The code is processed by a gadget server 
    and rendered in an IFRAME.</t>
       <t hangText="Type URL">Type URL gadgets only specify a base URL. A standard 
    set of parameters are added to this URL by the gadget server, which renders 
    the gadget in an IFRAME. The application to which the URL points must 
    include a referenced JavaScript library using a &lt;script&gt; tag as it 
    renders, to enable gadget APIs to be made available. Type URL gadgets can't 
    take advantage of all features, notably features that manipulate HTML and 
    JavaScript code directly. However, this gadget type has proven highly useful
    for turning existing web sites or applications into gadgets.</t>
      </list>
      Multiple Content sections may be specified in gadget XML. Each is
   labeled with one or more optional view identifiers, which allow the gadget
   to behave or appear differently depending on the context in which it's
   rendered. This context is provided by the gadget container.</t>
     <t hangText="Metadata">Any piece of information attached to a gadget, such
     as a title, author name, or description, that provides processing
     instructions to the Container, or otherwise does not directly impact
     gadget rendering.</t>
     <t hangText="Feature">A library or behavior that is provided by the
     Container and triggered by use of the /ModulePrefs/Require or
     /ModulePrefs/Optional tags. Gadget features are the primary extensibility mechanism employed by gadgets.
   They often direct a gadget server to make new JavaScript APIs available to
   rendering code, but may also manipulate the gadget's contents, for example
   to add extended syntax. Examples of gadget features include OpenSocial
   (provides gadgets with a rich set of social APIs), dynamic-height (enables
   gadgets to resize themselves to an appropriate height), and tabs (a UI
   library facilitating tabular navigation).</t>
     <t hangText="Message Bundles">Message bundles are XML documents containing localization
     information.  They allow developers to internationalize
   their gadgets simply by adding name/message mappings corresponding to
   whatever languages the developer chooses to support. These messages may be
   accessed programmatically through the core JavaScript APIs provided to all
   gadgets, or may be statically substituted into code using simple syntax.</t>
     <t hangText="User Preferences">Referred to as "user prefs" or "prefs",
     these represent configuration values for a User of the gadget. These are key/value pairs that form the basis of gadget
   configuration and persistence. They are most often manipulable by users of
   the gadget, and are persisted on behalf of a user so that the gadget has
   access to them across multiple rendering requests. The gadget container is
   typically responsible for providing their persistence for this data and an
   interface to edit it.</t>
     <t hangText="Gadget Specification XML">Generally referred to as "gadget
     spec", or simply a "gadget", this is the XML document that contains all
     the Metadata, Features, Message Bundles, User Preferences, and Content
     necessary to display a gadget to an end user. A gadget spec is authored by
     a Developer and made available through a public web server at a
     well-defined URL so that Containers may use this URL as a canonical
     reference for retrieving updates to the gadget.</t>
     <t hangText="Formal Schema Directory">Any system used to hold a repository
     of gadgets that may be installed by Users.</t>
     <t hangText="View">A presentation mode for a gadget.</t>
    </list>
  </section>
  <section title="Compliance"
           anchor="Compliance">
    <t>OpenSocial defines the following levels of compliance, each of
which defines an encapsulated set of capabilities. OpenSocial has been structured
this way to support a wide array of adoption use cases that are all considered compliant with the
specification. For example, it is possible to only offer social
APIs via REST and be considered a compliant OpenSocial Social API
Server. Likewise, some implementors may choose to leverage only the
gadget aspect of specification. In this case, they can be considered
to be a compliant OpenSocial Core Gadget Server.</t>
     <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Core API Server">To be considered a Core API Server, a site MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Core-API-Server">Core API Server Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="Core Gadget Container">To be considered a Gadget Container, a site MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Core-Gadget">Core Gadget Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="Social API Server">To be considered a Social API Server, a site MUST be a Core API Server and MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Social-API-Server">Social API Server Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="Social Gadget Container">To be considered a Social Gadget Container, a site MUST be a Core Gadget Container and MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Social-Gadget">Social Gadget Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="OpenSocial Container">To be considered an OpenSocial Container, a site MUST fulfill all the requirements for an Social API Server and a Social Gadget Container.</t>
     </list>
   <t>In all cases, a site MUST fulfill the requirements in <xref target="Extensions">Extensions</xref>.</t>
  </section>
  
  

<section title="Extensions" anchor="Extensions">

<t>
	The objective of the OpenSocial extension model is to allow the
	specification to mature by adding depth and richness to a set of
	existing features while at the same time fostering organic growth of
	new capability. That is, it should be possible to enhance existing
	features as well as add new ones. A robust extension model enables the
	OpenSocial community to manage the overall complexity of the
	specification in a clearly documented consistent manner. This model has
	the following benefits to the OpenSoicial community:</t>

	Keeps the core specification focused on defining the base programming
	model and social constructs.
	Lowers the barriers of entry thereby promoting adoption and increasing
	compatibility between implementations.
	Fosters the evolution of niche-features while avoiding anarchy.
	<t>This section defines the kinds of enhancements that we envision
		being made to OpenSocial, as well as the rules they must follow in
		order to be accepted into the specification. </t>
	<t>
	An extension is defined in a document, called an OpenSocial
	Enhancement (OE), with language and formatting that is consistent in
	terminology and semantics with the specification. As the extension
	develops, it MUST conform to the guidelines and life cycle defined in
	the OpenSocial Development Process. For example, extensions are
	required to provide a publically available prototype that demonstrates
	that it can be implemented as well as a corresponding set of test
	cases. Extensions MUST be defined in a manner that is consistent with
	the programming model defined in the versions of the specification to
	which they apply. Containers that offer OpenSocial extensions MUST
	adhere to the requirements specified in this specification as well as any
	requirements specified in the extension document. 
		
		
		
		</t>
	<t>Generally speaking, we anticipate OpenSocial to be extended
		following three patterns. Not coincidentally, these extension patterns
		follow the typical use cases of OpenSocial that are reflected in the
		structure of the specification. </t>
	<list style="symbols">
		<t>Adding a new gadget feature</t>
		<t>Extending the social data models</t>
		<t>Extending the protocol</t>
</list>

<section title="Adding a new Gadget Feature">
	<t>The OpenSocial programming model consists of a collection of
		Javascript APIs declared as features. There are two kinds of features,
		core and optional. For example, the core API gadgets.viewes.View
		defines how gadgets work with and request different amounts of real
		estate in the browser. An example optional feature is gadgets.skins..
		Because of the existing separation between core and optional features,
		OpenSocial is already layered to handle gadget extensions. In order to avoid undue burden on
		implementation of domain specific or container specific behavior,
		extensions MUST NOT be required. </t>
	<t>As OpenSocial becomes deployed more widely, the number of extensions
		will increase. It will be important that new features avoid clashing
		with those currently defined in the specification. New features that
		are proposed for inclusion of OpenSocial MUST NOT use any existing
		namespaces that are already part of the specification. It is the
		responsibility of the developer proposing the new feature to avoid
		namespace collisions. </t>
	<t>Features that are progressing through the OpenSocial enhancement
		lifecycle MUST include the lifecycle designator for the stage they are
		in as the suffix, delineated by a “.” of their name. For example,
		suppose that pub-sub is being proposed as a new feature. The community
		has been working on it and a proposal is available publically. The
		feature name should be: “pub-sub.incubating” </t>

<figure>
      <preamble> An example module definition would be:</preamble>
      <artwork xml:space="preserve">

&lt;Module&gt;
 &lt;ModulePrefs title="Social Activities World"
              icon="http://localhost:8080/gadgets/files/samplecontainer/examples/icon.png"&gt;
   &lt;Require feature="opensocial"&gt;&lt;/Require&gt;
   &lt;Require feature="pub-sub.incubating"&gt;&lt;/Require&gt;
 &lt;/ModulePrefs&gt; 
….
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>This intent is to clearly indicate gadget developers that the OpenSocial community has not officially adopted the feature. Upon acceptance of the proposal as part of the specification, the feature name MUST drop the life cycle designator.</t>
</section> <!-- Adding a new Gadget Feature -->

	<section title="Extending the social data models">
		<t>OpenSocial defines a set of data models that are used to represent
			the social constructs in your system, e.g. people. An set of fields
			has been defined for each one of these constructs. The initial
			motivation for these fields was driven primarily from the standpoint
			of Social Networking. </t>
		<t>Fortunately, as OpenSocial begins to be used in more specialized
			domains, the programming model is flexible enough to accommodate
			these new fields. However, care must be taken as extensions are
			introduced in order to avoid issues such as collisions in the
			attribute names of the returned JSON Objects. Therefore, extensions
			SHOULD use a prefix that uniquely identifies the extended fields. This prefix SHOULD be an underbar '_'. If
			a feature is also added as part of the exetension, the data model
			prefix SHOULD match a namespace declared in the Javascript. </t>
		<t>It is possible to simply append new fields into the existing
			models and some providers currently follow this approach. However, it is RECOMMENDED that extensions to the OpenSocial
			data models be encapsulated in their own node. This will provide a
			level of isolation and layering within the models and provide a
			consistent extension pattern. </t>
			
		<section title="A Note on XML Schema Validation">
		<t>
			In OpenSocial 1.0, the canonical XSDs do not contain extension points,
			e.g.xs:any. Therefore, XML instance documents of extensions that have
			added attributes ore elements to the data model or gadget metadata
			will not validate.
			Therefore, extensions MUST NOT require schema validation. Containers that are
			not supporting extensions MAY validate the gadget metadata and the
			data models.
		</t>
	</section>
			
	
		<section title="Extensions Example" anchor="extensionsExample">
		
		<t>  	Below is an example of how the Person model has been
				extended by two fictional organizations, Acme and DevWorld. Acme has been
				using OpenSocial for some time, and has extended the modely by
				appending a field, "Employee Number" directly into the data model. This approach shoudl
				be used for
				backwards compatibility with existing extensions. As new extensions are
				proposed, they should follow the pattern illustrated by DevWorld,
				which creates a containing element, "devWorldData", for their additions to the model.</t>

	<figure>
		<preamble>
			Assuming the extensions have been made available via
			features to the container, here is the example REST call that would
			retreive the data.
			</preamble>
		<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
http://someOpenSocialContainer/social/rest/people/john.doe/@self?format=xml&fields=id&fields=name&fields=acme_EmployeeNumber&fields=devworld_nickname&fields=devworld_platform
		]]></artwork>
		<postamble>Notice in the request the use of the name and underbar
	prefix, e.g. "devworld_", to help avoid collisions. In this example,
	DevWorld allows their users to assign nicknames. Without a prefix, this
	would clash with OpenSocial's Person nickname. 
		</postamble>
		</figure>		
				
	<figure>
	<preamble>
		The result of this request will produce an XML document with the
		following structure.
			</preamble>
	<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[			
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<response xmlns="http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial"><person xmlns="http://ns.opensocial.org/2008/opensocial">
  <acme__EmployeeNumber>1122998877</acme__EmployeeNumber>
  <devWorldData>
    <entry>
      <key>devworld_nickname</key>
      <value>The Wiz...</value>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <key>devworld_platform</key>
      <value>Mac</value>
    </entry>
  </devWorldData>
  <id>john.doe</id>
  <name>
    <familyName>Doe</familyName>
    <formatted>John Doe</formatted>
    <givenName>John</givenName>
  </name>
</person>
</response>
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
				
		<figure>
			<preamble>
			Omitting the "type=XML" query parameter from the request will return a JSON document.  
			</preamble>
			<artwork><![CDATA[
[{"id":"viewer","data":{"acme_EmployeeNumber":"1122998877","devWorldData":{"devworld_nickname":"The Wiz..."},"id":"john.doe","name":{"formatted":"John Doe","familyName":"Doe","givenName":"John"},"displayName":"Johnny"}}]
			]]>
			</artwork>
			</figure>
		
		
				
		</section> <!-- Extensions Example -->
	
	
	</section> <!-- Extending the social data models -->

<section title="Extending the protocol">
	<t>
	In some cases, it will be necessary to add APIs to support
	additional
	use cases outside the initial intent of the specification.
	For example,
	an alternate security model or
	payment API may
	be
	introduced.
	In these
	scenarios developers MAY extend OpenSocial by
	introducing new
	APIs.
	These kinds of additions to OpenSocial are called "protocol
	extensions"
	becuase they introduce new APIs. It is important that these
	APIs be
	consistent with the existing programming model. Protocol
	extensions MUST
	maintain the semantics of the OpenSocial and MUST NOT
	modify any API
	defined by the specification. Protocol exetensions
	MUST
	provide
	endpoints in the required protocols as defined by the
	specification,
	e.g. XML, JSON, ATOM.

	Protocol extensions SHOULD provide
	extensions for each level of compliance as defined by the OpenSocial
	specificaiton, e.g. REST APIs for the OpenSocial server as
	well as constructs to support OSML and templating. 	

		
	</t>


</section> <!-- Extending the protocol -->

</section> <!-- Extensions Root -->



  
  
  
  
 </middle>
 <back>
  <references>
   <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
    <front>
     <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
     <author initials='S.'
             surname='Bradner'
             fullname='Scott Bradner'>
      <organization abbrev='HarvardU'>Harvard University</organization>
     </author>
     <date month='March'
           year='1997' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='2119' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC2606'>
    <front>
     <title>Reserved Top Level DNS Names</title>
     <author initials='D.'
             surname='Eastlake'
             fullname='Donald E. Eastlake 3rd'>
      <organization abbrev='IBM'>IBM</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='A.'
             surname='Panitz'
             fullname='Aliza R. Panitz'></author>
     <date month='June'
           year='1999' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='2606' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Core-Gadget"
              target="./Core-Gadget.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Core Gadget Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Core-API-Server"
              target="./Core-API-Server.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Core API Server Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Social-Gadget"
              target="./Social-Gadget.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Social Gadget Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Social-API-Server"
              target="./Social-API-Server.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Social API Server Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
  </references>
 </back>
</rfc>
