<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./OpenSocial.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
"http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="full3978"
     docName="opensocial-specification-draft"
     xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">
 <front>
  <title abbrev="OpenSocial Specificaton">OpenSocial Specification (draft)</title>
  <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group'>
   <address>
    <email>opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  <date month="April"
        year="2009" />
  <area>General</area>
  <keyword>OpenSocial</keyword>
  <keyword>social networking</keyword>
  <keyword>REST</keyword>
  <keyword>XML</keyword>
  <keyword>Extensible Markup Language</keyword>
  <keyword>JSON</keyword>
  <keyword>JavaScript Object Notation</keyword>
  <keyword>Atom</keyword>
 </front>
 <middle>
  <section title="Notation and Conventions">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in 
   <xref target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>. Domain name examples use 
   <xref target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref>.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Overview">
   <t>OpenSocial is a set of APIs for building social applications that run on
   the web. OpenSocial's goal is to make more apps available to more users, by
   providing a common API that can be used in many different contexts.
   Developers can create applications, using standard JavaScript and HTML, that
   run on social websites that have implemented the OpenSocial APIs. These
   websites, known as OpenSocial containers, allow developers to access their
   social information; in return they receive a large suite of applications for
   their users.</t>
   <t>The OpenSocial APIs expose methods for accessing information about
   people, their friends, and their data, within the context of a container.
   This means that when running an application on Orkut, you'll be interacting
   with your Orkut friends, while running the same application on MySpace lets
   you interact with your MySpace friends. For more information on the types of
   information exposed by the OpenSocial API, see the Key concepts section.</t>
   <t>This document describes the concepts and principles behind the OpenSocial
   JavaScript APIs. It is a complement to the JavaScript API Reference, which
   covers the details of specific methods and parameters. This document does
   not describe any particular implementation of the API.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Compliance"
           anchor="Compliance">
    <t>OpenSocial defines the following levels of compliance, each of
which defines an encapsulated set of capabilities. OpenSocial has been structured
this way to support a wide array of adoption use cases that are all considered compliant with the
specification. For example, it is possible to only offer social
APIs via REST and be considered a compliant OpenSocial Social API
Server. Likewise, some implementors may choose to leverage only the
gadget aspect of specification. In this case, they can be considered
to be a compliant OpenSocial Core Gadget Server.</t>
     <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Core API Server">To be considered a Core API Server, a site MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Core-API-Server">Core API Server Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="Core Gadget Container">To be considered a Gadget Container, a site MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Core-Gadget">Core Gadget Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="Social API Server">To be considered a Social API Server, a site MUST be a Core API Server and MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Social-API-Server">Social API Server Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="Social Gadget Container">To be considered a Social Gadget Container, a site MUST be a Core Gadget Container and MUST fulfill all the requirements defined in the <xref target="Social-Gadget">Social Gadget Specification</xref>.</t>
      <t hangText="OpenSocial Container">To be considered an OpenSocial Container, a site MUST fulfill all the requirements for an Social API Server and a Social Gadget Container.</t>
     </list>
   <t>In all cases, a site MUST fulfill the requirements in <xref target="Extensions">Extensions</xref>.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Extensions">
    <t><x:highlight>[TODO: Add extensions section]</x:highlight></t>
  </section>
 </middle>
 <back>
  <references>
   <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
    <front>
     <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
     <author initials='S.'
             surname='Bradner'
             fullname='Scott Bradner'>
      <organization abbrev='HarvardU'>Harvard University</organization>
     </author>
     <date month='March'
           year='1997' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='2119' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor='RFC2606'>
    <front>
     <title>Reserved Top Level DNS Names</title>
     <author initials='D.'
             surname='Eastlake'
             fullname='Donald E. Eastlake 3rd'>
      <organization abbrev='IBM'>IBM</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials='A.'
             surname='Panitz'
             fullname='Aliza R. Panitz'></author>
     <date month='June'
           year='1999' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='RFC'
                value='2606' />
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Core-Gadget"
              target="./Core-Gadget.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Core Gadget Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Core-API-Server"
              target="./Core-API-Server.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Core API Server Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Social-Gadget"
              target="./Social-Gadget.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Social Gadget Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="Social-API-Server"
              target="./Social-API-Server.xml">
    <front>
     <title>OpenSocial Social API Server Specification</title>
     <author fullname='OpenSocial and Gadgets Specification Group &lt;opensocial-and-gadgets-spec@googlegroups.com&gt;'>
     </author>
     <date month='December'
           year='2009' />
    </front>
   </reference>
  </references>
 </back>
</rfc>
